<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Little Umbrellas</title><link href="http://dlukes.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://dlukes.github.io/feeds/os-x-tips.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://dlukes.github.io/</id><updated>2016-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Configuring Emacs Daemon on Mac OS X</title><link href="http://dlukes.github.io/emacs-daemon-osx.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>dlukes</name></author><id>tag:dlukes.github.io,2016-02-20:emacs-daemon-osx.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I know I promised this article a loooong time ago (June 2014, when I first got a
Mac, to judge by the previous timestamp in the header of this file), but since
the historically attested readership of this blog is 2 + a bunch of my facebook
friends who I nagged to read
&lt;a href="http://dlukes.github.io/unicode.html"&gt;my attempt at explaining character encodings to non-technical people&lt;/a&gt;,
I don't suppose it's as if a legion of fans have been restlessly looking forward
to this one ;) Nevertheless, the distinct advantage is that my OS X Emacs setup
has had the opportunity to grow more mature and also much simpler in the
meantime, which means that if a third reader accidentally stumbles over this
note (exploding my ratings...), they might actually find something genuinely
useful here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presents a way to &lt;strong&gt;start Emacs Daemon&lt;/strong&gt; (a persistent Emacs
session) &lt;strong&gt;from the GUI&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;subsequently connect to it&lt;/strong&gt; (creating frames on
demand) using an &lt;strong&gt;Automator script&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;benefit&lt;/strong&gt; is that you &lt;strong&gt;incur
startup time lag only once&lt;/strong&gt; (when you start the daemon) while still being able
to &lt;strong&gt;close all frames&lt;/strong&gt; when you're not using Emacs, keeping a &lt;strong&gt;clean
workspace&lt;/strong&gt;. This is &lt;strong&gt;especially useful&lt;/strong&gt; if your Emacs is &lt;strong&gt;heavily
customized&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;loading it takes a while&lt;/strong&gt;. Another &lt;strong&gt;benefit&lt;/strong&gt; is that
whenever you open a frame connected to an Emacs daemon, &lt;strong&gt;all your previously
open buffers are still there as you left them&lt;/strong&gt; (as opposed to opening a fresh
instance of Emacs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skim over the code blocks to get the
important gist without the verbose sauce. Tested on OS X 10.11 El Capitan, with
Homebrew Emacs and Spacemacs config.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why Emacs Daemon, why this post&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing Emacs on a Mac in and of itself is not that much of a problem --
there are several options, ranging from Homebrew and Macports to
&lt;a href="http://emacsformacosx.com/"&gt;Emacs for Mac OS X&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/railwaycat/emacs-mac-port"&gt;Emacs Mac Port&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://aquamacs.org/"&gt;Aquamacs&lt;/a&gt;. The last two in this list have some OS X
specific tweaks (smooth scrolling, tabs, adapted keyboard shortcuts), which
makes them perhaps more appealing out of the box but also less extensible, as
some of the information out there about generic Emacs might not apply to them as
straightforwardly or indeed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, if you want to tinker with your Emacs config, it's a good
idea to stick with &lt;a href="http://brew.sh/"&gt;Homebrew's&lt;/a&gt; fairly conservative version of
Emacs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;$ brew update
$ brew install emacs --with-cocoa
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# this step gets you a standard OS X launcher icon&lt;/span&gt;
$ brew linkapps emacs
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now that you've got Emacs, and especially if you're transferring some heavy
customization over from say Linux, you might be unhappy that each time you start
it from cold, it takes a while, typically a few seconds. That's what &lt;code&gt;emacs
--daemon&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;emacsclient&lt;/code&gt; are for: &lt;strong&gt;Emacs&lt;/strong&gt; is run as a &lt;strong&gt;daemon&lt;/strong&gt; in the
&lt;strong&gt;backround&lt;/strong&gt; and you connect to it with &lt;strong&gt;client frames&lt;/strong&gt; that &lt;strong&gt;spawn almost
instantly&lt;/strong&gt;. This also means that you can close all existing frames to keep your
workspace clean if you won't be using Emacs for a while (hard to imagine, right,
since you can even
&lt;a href="https://github.com/vibhavp/emacs-xkcd"&gt;read xkcd from inside Emacs&lt;/a&gt;) and then
whip up a frame at the speed of a thought when need arises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is all
&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/5578718/1826241"&gt;easy to achieve when using the terminal&lt;/a&gt;,
but since you probably bought that Mac in great part for its shiny pretty
elegant ergonomic GUI, you might want Emacs to use GUI frames instead of
terminal ones and connect to the Emacs daemon (or start it if it's not running)
by just clicking on an app icon in the launcher or finding it from Spotlight.
That's where Automator comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;An Automator script&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.macosxautomation.com/automator/"&gt;Automator&lt;/a&gt; is a built-in OS X app
for creating custom automated user workflows for just about any installed app
you might have or even OS functionality. Among other things, this means that it
allows you to wrap the daemon auto-start functionality available from the
terminal (as described in the previous paragraph) into an app launchable from
the GUI. Let's get down to business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch Automator and create a new document. Select &lt;em&gt;Application&lt;/em&gt; as its type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search the Actions palette on the left for the &lt;em&gt;Run Shell Script&lt;/em&gt; action and
   add it to your Automator document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Run Shell Script&lt;/em&gt; building block, change the following:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set &lt;em&gt;Shell&lt;/em&gt; to the shell you're using and whose init files have thus the
  &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; correctly set to the &lt;code&gt;emacs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;emacsclient&lt;/code&gt; executables (if
  you're using Homebrew, it probably told you how to properly set up your
  &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; as a post-install step)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set &lt;em&gt;Pass input&lt;/em&gt; to "as arguments" (if you then
  &lt;a href="http://osxdaily.com/2013/08/08/change-default-application-open-files-mac-os-x/"&gt;set this Automator app as the default for opening a given type of file&lt;/a&gt;,
  you'll be able to use &lt;code&gt;emacsclient&lt;/code&gt; to open files by double-clicking on them
  in Finder)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, paste in the following code snippet and save the app e.g. as
   &lt;code&gt;EmacsClient.app&lt;/code&gt;, preferably in your Applications folder so that it is
   easily accessible from the launcher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;nohup emacsclient --no-wait -c -a emacs &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, your Automator EmacsClient.app should look something like
this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EmacsClient.app" src="images/emacsclientapp.png" style="max-width: 100%;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of the command that you might want to tweak based on your particular
Emacs setup is &lt;code&gt;emacsclient --no-wait -c -a emacs&lt;/code&gt;; mine is optimized to work
with mostly stock Spacemacs config (see below). If it doesn't work, you might
also want to try a simple &lt;code&gt;emacsclient -c -a ""&lt;/code&gt; and variations; a good
debugging technique is to try these out in the terminal: as soon as you get the
line working there, it'll start working in the Automator task as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;"$@"&lt;/code&gt; is just the list of files (if any) passed to Emacs to open (the
aforementioned double-click in Finder use case). The rest is some black magic to
ensure that the shell which spawns the Emacs process (because this Automator app
is after all, at heart, only a shell script) totally and utterly disowns it, so
that the shell script is allowed to return and the Automator task completes as
soon as Emacs has started (or the client has spawned a new frame). Otherwise,
you'd end up with an irritating spinning cog wheel in your notification area
which would stay there until you completely quit Emacs. Which is probably not
what you want, since you're undergoing all this hassle in the first place to get
a zen, distraction-free Emacs experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details of the various incantations are discussed in
&lt;a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6474971?start=0&amp;amp;tstart=0"&gt;this Apple forum thread&lt;/a&gt;,
but let's have a whirlwind tour for the moderately interested (my knowledge of
Unix processes is far from perfect, so feel free to correct me on these points!):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nohup&lt;/code&gt; makes the parent process (the shell) disown the child process
   (Emacs), so that the shell can exit without killing Emacs as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;/dev/null&lt;/code&gt; redirects standard output to oblivion and &lt;code&gt;2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1&lt;/code&gt; redirects
   standard error to standard output (i.e. also to oblivion), which persuades
   Automator that you're really not expecting to hear from the process via these
   standard streams ever again, so there's no point in keeping the shell script
   running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the final &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; runs the command in the background, which ensures control of
   the shell is returned to the user as soon as the process is spawned; since
   there are no additional commands in the shell script and all remaining ties
   have been severed (see points 1 and 2 above), Automator finally agrees that
   the task has probably done all it was expected to do and exits it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whew! That's it. It's really not that complicated, it's just that my prose is
verbose, so it makes it look like there's lots and lots to do. Trust me, there
isn't. My first go at solving this usability problem -- the one I originally
wanted to post way back in 2014 -- was a lengthy, godawful Applescript prone to
subtle breakage. This is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the ability to just use a single GUI app for transparently launching &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;
connecting to the Emacs daemon is pure bliss. While you're at it, for an even
better Emacs experience, go fetch the excellent
&lt;a href="http://spacemacs.org"&gt;Spacemacs Emacs config distribution&lt;/a&gt;, which pulls this
venerable piece of software screaming into the 21st century. &lt;strong&gt;The best editor
is neither Vim nor Emacs, its Vim + Emacs!&lt;/strong&gt; The addictive icing of Vim modal
editing on the outside, a creamy Elisp core -- what more could you want from
life? ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh and if, like me, you love
&lt;a href="https://github.com/nashamri/spacemacs-logo"&gt;Spacemacs' snappy icon&lt;/a&gt; with the
Evil spaceship over planet Emacs -- or if, like me, you have OCD -- you'll
&lt;a href="http://www.macworld.co.uk/how-to/mac-software/how-change-os-x-yosemites-icons-3597494/"&gt;definitely want to switch your Emacs logo to the Spacemacs one&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="osx"></category><category term="gui"></category><category term="emacs"></category><category term="daemon"></category><category term="emacsclient"></category><category term="spacemacs"></category><category term="automator"></category></entry><entry><title>Filling (hardwrapping) paragraphs in Airmail with `par`</title><link href="http://dlukes.github.io/fill-par-in-airmail.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>dlukes</name></author><id>tag:dlukes.github.io,2014-06-27:fill-par-in-airmail.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jump directly to &lt;a href="#solution"&gt;the proposed solution&lt;/a&gt;. Tested on OS X 10.9
(Mavericks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Back story&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airmail is a great application -- being very happy with Gmail's in-browser UI,
it's honestly the first e-mail desktop client that I ever felt even remotely
tempted to use. It has:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a sleek, functional design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;almost flawless integration with Gmail (except for categories -- but there's
a
&lt;a href="http://airmail.tenderapp.com/help/discussions/suggestion-new-features/396-workaround-for-gmail-categories"&gt;not-too-hackish way&lt;/a&gt;
to deal with those)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Markdown compose mode (yay!) -- and tons of other good stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially that last feature almost got me sold -- you see, I like my e-mail
hardwrapped (what Emacs calls "filling paragraphs"), because most of the time,
I view it on monitors that are too wide for soft line wrapping to achieve a
comfortable text width.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, Airmail's layout deals with this issue very elegantly, but I know
I won't be using only Airmail. Plus there are the obvious
&lt;a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/MailingListEtiquette#Line_Wrapping"&gt;netiquette issues&lt;/a&gt;
-- lines "should be" wrapped at 72 characters etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Gmail, I therefore use plain-text compose, which is fine for the purposes
described above, but frustrating whenever you want to apply formatting
(obviously, you can't -- it's plain text). I tried using the usual replacements
for formatting like stars &amp;amp; co., and I don't know about your grandma, but
&lt;em&gt;mine&lt;/em&gt; certainly doesn't take *...* to mean emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the Markdown compose mode in Airmail would solve my problems -- I
could apply formatting if and when I wanted (using the frankly more streamlined
process of &lt;em&gt;typing it in&lt;/em&gt; rather than fumbling around for the right button in
the GUI) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fill my paragraphs, because I somehow automatically assumed
there'd by a hard-wrap feature like in any decent editor (read: emacs or
vi). Markdown is plain text after all, isn't it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, as of yet, &lt;strong&gt;there isn't&lt;/strong&gt;. There isn't even one for the
plain-text compose mode, as far as I'm aware. So I added my two cents to
&lt;a href="http://feedback.airmailapp.com/forums/209001-airmail-mac-1-2/suggestions/4078595-add-line-wrap-for-plain-text-mails"&gt;this feature request thread&lt;/a&gt;
and went back to the Gmail in-browser UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Solution &lt;a name="solution"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I realized (it took me a while, I'm still very much an OS X newbie):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in OS X, you can define custom actions with shortcuts&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for any
   application using Automator Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these actions can be easily set to receive text selected in the application
   as input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these actions can also involve shell scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there already &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a great (command line) program for filling paragraphs --
   it's called &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt;, and as much as I admire what Airmail's developers have
   achieved, it's unlikely that they'd come up with a more sophisticated
   hard-wrapping algorithm than &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt;'s simply as a side project for Airmail
   (see the EXAMPLES section in &lt;code&gt;man par&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, you can have hard-wrapping in Markdown or plain-text Airmail
compose at your fingertips in no time flat. If you don't have &lt;code&gt;homebrew&lt;/code&gt;, start
by installing that (or any other ports manager that will allow you to install
&lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt;; I'll assume &lt;code&gt;homebrew&lt;/code&gt; below) by pasting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;    ruby -e &amp;quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)&amp;quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;at a Terminal prompt. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;brew install par&lt;/code&gt; at a Terminal prompt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;open Automator (e.g. by typing "Automator" into Spotlight) and create a new
   Service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;select the applications for which you want the service to be active (for me,
   that's just Airmail) and tick the "Output replaces selected text" box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;drag the "Run Shell Script" action onto the workflow canvas, and as the
   shell script, paste in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;PARINIT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;rTbgqR B=.,?_A_a Q=_s&amp;gt;|&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; /usr/local/bin/par 79
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the $PARINIT environment variable contains the default recommended
  settings for &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt; (if you want to customize its behavior, you can -- good
  luck wrapping your head around &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt;'s manpage, though)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you should set the full path to the &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt; executable, the shell spawned by
  the Service might not inherit your $PATH -- for &lt;code&gt;par&lt;/code&gt; installed via
  &lt;code&gt;homebrew&lt;/code&gt;, it's &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin/par&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the parameter at the end is the max number of characters per
  line -- mailing list etiquette stipulates 72, I personally prefer the
  pythonesque 79, but it's your choice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, your service should look something like in the screenshot
below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fill Paragraph Service in Automator" src="images/fill-par.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save it, open Keyboard preferences (type "Keyboard" into Spotlight), navigate
to Shortcuts → Services → Text and set a keyboard shortcut for your newly
created Service, e.g. Cmd+Opt+P. Next time you compose an e-mail in Airmail,
just select the entire text when you're done (Cmd+A), press Cmd+Opt+P, and
voilà! Your lines have been hardwrapped, your paragraphs filled :) (Same thing,
I know.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the shortcut doesn't appear to work&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, try fiddling around with it,
resetting it (maybe the one you've chosen conflicts with a pre-existing one?),
restarting Airmail, logging out and back in, rebooting... The custom shortcut
part is unfortunately the least reliable aspect of this whole setup. Automator
is a great idea, I was pleasantly surprised by it when I started using OS X a
few days back, but it could seriously use some bug-squashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you fail miserably at getting the shortcut to work, you can &lt;strong&gt;still access
your fill paragraph service via the menu&lt;/strong&gt; (select the text you want to
hard-wrap, then navigate to Airmail → Services → &amp;lt;name of your fill paragraph
service&gt;). Clicking around in a GUI is tedious (though hey -- it's the Apple
way after all, isn't it?), but it shouldn't be too much of a bother since you
need to do it only once per e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom line&lt;/strong&gt;: I am now officially completely sold on Airmail (even bought
the released version instead of using the free beta) and look forward to the
joy of using it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: In order to have the &lt;strong&gt;least trouble possible getting the shell script up
and running as a Service&lt;/strong&gt;, two rules of thumb:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave it completely up to OS X where it stores the Service (.workflow)
   file. This will probably be in &lt;code&gt;~/Library/Services&lt;/code&gt;, and I learnt the hard
   way not to tinker with it -- if &lt;code&gt;Services&lt;/code&gt; is a symlink instead of a real
   directory, the OS won't discover new Service files (though old ones will
   still be accessible).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Service doesn't show up in the keyboard shortcuts menu after
   creation, try refreshing the service list with
   &lt;code&gt;/System/Library/CoreServices/pbs -update&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those shortcuts are in fact quite buggy, especially those that you want
to be global (not specific to a concrete app) -- at least on Mavericks (OS
X 10.9). They tend to get disabled on a whim, especially if you tinker with
them, and are a pain to get working again (login, logout, reboot -- anything
goes). If anyone knows why, please let me know!&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="osx"></category><category term="par"></category><category term="airmail"></category><category term="automator"></category><category term="services"></category><category term="fill"></category><category term="wrap"></category><category term="lines"></category></entry></feed>